My name is Tom,
اسمي توم،
and I've come here today to come clean
ولقد جئت هنا اليوم لأعترف لكم
about what I do for money.
بما أقوم به لكسب المال.
Basically, I use my mouth in strange ways
أنا أساسا أستخدم فمي بطرق غريبة
in exchange for cash.
بمقابل مادي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I usually do this kind of thing in seedy downtown bars
وعادة ما أقوم بهذه الأشياء في الحانات البائسة في وسط المدينة
and on street corners,
وفي زوايا الشوارع،
so this mightn't be the most appropriate setting,
لذا قد لا يكون هذا الإعداد الأكثر ملاءمة،
but I'd like to give you guys a bit of a demonstration
لكنني أود أن أعرض عليكم عينة
about what I do.
مما أقوم به.
(Beatboxing)
(بيتبوكسينغ)
And now, for my next number,
والآن، وفي أدائي التالي،
I'd like to return to the classics.
أود العودة إلى الكلاسيكيات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We're going to take it back,
سأعود بكم إلى الماضي،
way back,
إلى الماضي السحيق،
back into time.
عودة في الزمن.
(Beatboxing: "Billie Jean")
(بيتبوكسينغ: "بيلي جين")
♫ Billie Jean is not my lover ♫
♫ بيلي جين ليس بحبيبي ♫
♫ She's just a girl who claims that I am the one ♫
♫ إنها مجرد فتاة تدعي أنني أنا المختار ♫
♫ But the kid is not my son ♫
♫ لكن الطفل ليس بابني ♫
(Applause) All right.
(تصفيق) حسنًا.
Wassup.
ما الجديد.
Thank you very much, TEDx.
أشكركم جزيل الشكر، TEDx.
If you guys haven't figured it out already,
إذا يا رفاق إن لم تدركوها بالفعل،
my name's Tom Thum, and I'm a beatboxer,
إسمي توم ثام وأنا مؤدي بيتبوكس،
which means all the sounds that you just heard
وذلك يعني أن جميع الأصوات التي سمعتموها للتو
were made entirely using just my voice,
قد تم إنتاجها بالكامل باستخدام صوتي،
and the only thing was my voice.
وصوتي كان الشيء الوحيد.
And I can assure you
ويمكنني أن أؤكد لكم
there are absolutely no effects
أنه لم تكن هناك أي مؤثرات على الإطلاق
on this microphone whatsoever.
على هذا الميكروفون على الإطلاق.
And I'm very, very stoked —
وأنا متحمس للغاية —
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You guys are just applauding for everything. It's great.
يا رفاق أنتم تصفقون لكل شيء، أمر عظيم.
Look at this, Mom! I made it!
انظري إلى هذا، أمي! لقد حققت هدفي!
I'm very, very stoked to be here today,
أنا متحمس جدا لتواجدي هنا اليوم،
representing my kinfolk
ممثلا أهلي
and all those that haven't managed to make a career
وكل من لم يستطع أن يجعل من قدرته الفطرية في إحداث
out of an innate ability for inhuman noisemaking.
أصوات غير بشرية، مسيرة مهنية ناجحة
Because it is a bit of a niche market,
لأنها نوعا ما سوق متخصصة،
and there's not much work going on,
وليس هناك الكثير من الأعمال الجارية فيها،
especially where I'm from.
لا سيما من حيث أتيت.
You know, I'm from Brisbane,
كما تعلمون، أنا من بريزبن،
which is a great city to live in.
وهي مدينة عظيمة للعيش فيها.
Yeah! All right! Most of Brisbane's here. That's good.
نعم! حسنًا! معظم ساكنة بريزبن موجودون هنا. هذا جيد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, I'm from Brizzy,
كما تعلمون، أنا من بريزبن،
which is a great city to live in,
وهي مدينة عظيمة للعيش فيها.
but let's be honest --
ولكن دعونا نكون صادقين -
it's not exactly the cultural hub of the Southern Hemisphere.
هي ليست بالضبط المحور الثقافي لنصف الكرة الجنوبي.
So I do a lot of my work outside Brisbane
لذا أؤدي الكثير من أعمالي خارج بريزبن
and outside Australia,
وخارج أستراليا،
and so the pursuit of this crazy passion of mine
ولذلك فإن السعي وراء شغفي المجنون هذا
has enabled me to see
قد مكنني من رؤية
so many amazing places in the world.
الكثير من الأماكن المدهشة في العالم.
So I'd like to share with you, if I may, my experiences.
لذا أود أن أشاطركم، إن سمحتم، تجاربي.
So ladies and gentlemen,
إذن سيداتي سادتي،
I would like to take you on a journey
أود أن آخذكم في رحلة
throughout the continents
عبر القارات
and throughout sound itself.
وعبر الصوت نفسه.
We start our journey in the central deserts.
نبدأ رحلتنا من الصحاري المركزية.
(Didgeridoo)
(ديد جيريدو)
(Airplane)
(طائرة)
India.
الهند.
(Beatboxing)
(بيتبوكسينغ)
(Sitar)
(سيتار)
China.
الصين.
(Guzheng)
(غوتشنيغ)
(Beatboxing)
(بيتبوكسينغ)
Germany.
ألمانيا.
Party, party, yeah.
حفلة، حفلة، ياي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And before we reach our final destination,
وقبل أن نصل إلى وجهتنا النهائية،
ladies and gentlemen,
سيداتي سادتي،
I would like to share with you some technology
أود أن أطلعكم على بعض التكنولوجيا
that I brought all the way from the thriving metropolis of Brisbane.
التي أحضرتها من عاصمة بريزبان المزدهرة.
These things in front of me here are called Kaoss Pads,
وهذه الأشياء أمامي تدعى ألواح كاوس،
and they allow me to do a whole lot of different things
وهي تسمح لي بالقيام بالكثير من الأمور المختلفة
with my voice.
بصوتي.
For example, the one on the left here
على سبيل المثال، التي على اليسار هنا
allows me to add
تسمح لي بإضافة
a little bit of reverb to my sound,
القليل من الصدى لصوتي،
which gives me that --
والذي يعطيني تلك -
(Trumpet) --
(البوق)-
flavor.
النكهة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the other ones here,
والأخرى هنا،
I can use them in unison
يمكن أن أستخدمها في تناغم
to mimic the effect of a drum machine
لمحاكاة مؤثرات آلة الطبل
or something like that.
أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
I can sample in my own sounds and I can play it back
أستطيع أخذ عينة من أصواتي الخاصة وإعادة تشغيلها لاحقا
just by hitting the pads here.
فقط عن طريق ضرب الألواح هنا.
(Noises)
(ضوضاء)
TEDx.
TEDx.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I got way too much time on my hands.
لدي الكثير جدا من وقت الفراغ.
And last but not least,
وأخيراً وليس آخراً،
the one on my right here allows me to
التي على يميني هنا تسمح لي بالتشغيل
loop loop loop loop loop loop loop loop
الحلقي الحلقي الحلقي الحلقي الحلقي الحلقي الحلقي الحلقي
my voice.
لصوتي.
So with all that in mind, ladies and gentlemen,
وبأخذ كل هذا بعين الاعتبار، سيداتي سادتي،
I would like to take you on a journey
أود أن آخذكم في رحلة
to a completely separate part of Earth
لجزء منفصل تماما من الأرض
as I transform the Sydney Opera House
وأنا أحول دار أوبرا سيدني
into a smoky downtown jazz bar.
إلى حانة جاز مفعمة بالدخان في وسط المدينة.
All right boys, take it away.
حسنا يا شباب، لنبدأ العرض.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to introduce you
سيداتي سادتي، أود أن أقدم لكم
to a very special friend of mine,
صديقا لي خاصا جداً،
one of the greatest double bassists I know.
واحد من أعظم العازفين المزدوجين الذين أعرفهم.
Mr. Smokey Jefferson, let's take it for a walk. Come on, baby.
السيد سموكي جيفرسون، دعونا نذهب به في نزهة. هيا بنا عزيزي.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
All right, ladies and gentlemen,
حسنا، سيداتي سادتي،
I'd like to introduce you to the star of the show,
أود أن أقدم لكم نجم العرض،
one of the greatest jazz legends of our time.
واحدة من أعظم أساطير الجاز في عصرنا.
Music lovers and jazz lovers alike,
عشاق الموسيقى ومحبي الجاز على حد السواء،
please give a warm hand of applause
رجاء صفقوا بحرارة
for the one and only Mr. Peeping Tom. Take it away.
للواحد والوحيد، السيد بيبينغ توم. فليتقدم مشكورا.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. Thank you very much.
شكرا. شكرا جزيلا.